<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Julien Delange</title>
    <description>Passe moi le shell</description>
    <link>http://julien.gunnm.org/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://julien.gunnm.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2023 02:29:12 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2023 02:29:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.3.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Acquired</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, I sold &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.codiga.io&quot;&gt;Codiga&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.datadoghq.com&quot;&gt;Datadog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This story started in 2018 when I realized that if I did not attempt to build a company on my own, I would regret it until I died.
I started slowly and eventually left everything to dedicate all my attention to this project.
From 2021 to 2023, I spent two years focusing solely on building this company. I enjoyed the thrills of flying high and going through many rough turbulences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not been easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made a ton of mistakes and I lost a lot along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I have no regret about what I accomplished. I lived this story on my own terms. And this is what matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not start this company to become rich or have more influence. I did it to have the freedom to make something meaningful. I also did it to show that startups can be created outside of Silicon Valley. And that you do not need to have a team of engineers from MIT, Berkeley, Stanford or a FAANG company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am proud of what I did and what we accomplished as a team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To everyone that took part in this ride: thank you. Whoever you are - current or past team members, investors, and users: thank you for everything you did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To everyone that did not believe in me, ignored me or dumped me: thank you. You made me question myself, and I became a better person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s now time for me to move to NYC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still have much to learn and I can’t wait to open this new chapter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;840&quot; height=&quot;473&quot; style=&quot;display:block; margin: 0 auto;&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1Vmq8kCAYng?start=3257&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 17 Apr 2023 06:10:20 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://julien.gunnm.org/acquisition/company/startup/2023/04/17/acquired/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://julien.gunnm.org/acquisition/company/startup/2023/04/17/acquired/</guid>
        
        <category>startup</category>
        
        <category>aquisition</category>
        
        <category>codiga</category>
        
        <category>datadog</category>
        
        
        <category>acquisition</category>
        
        <category>company</category>
        
        <category>startup</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Principles</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Last year, I read &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/3KAsiig&quot;&gt;Principles&lt;/a&gt; by Ray Dalio, which enumerates principles Dalio used throughout his life to drive decision-making. It heavily influenced me to guide my business and personal decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recently, I read &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/3MmOb5M&quot;&gt;Good to Great&lt;/a&gt; by Jim Collins, which describes the characteristics of great companies (as opposed to good companies).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many commonalities between these books. They both describe principles and characteristics of what drives a company or life to success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to do the exercise to gather my thoughts and enumerate the principles that influenced me the most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;its-about-the-who-not-the-what&quot;&gt;It’s about the who, not the what&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important in your life or business is the who, not the what. “Good to great” shows that all great companies care about the “who” before doing anything. Great companies were not producing anything initially: they focused on whom to hire and whom to fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The very same principle is true in our personal life. Our relations and interactions with others shape our decisions. Our friends and life partner can accelerate our lives or be a weight we have to carry until we die. It’s essential to select the persons you build a relationship with and help you drive you to success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Good to Great” makes the metaphor of a bus: before you even start driving the bus, make sure you onboard the right people inside the bus. When a careless, underperforming employee is on the bus, they will not help to drive it in the right direction (this is even more true if the person is an executive). When your partner is not supportive, this will put you down, affect your well-being not support your personal growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One final note is that the “right” people are not whom you agree with constantly. The “right” people will support your professional or personal growth and drive you to success. You need disagreement (either at work or in a relationship); it is crucial to be open-minded, discuss different opinions, value their merits, and move forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;embrace-reality&quot;&gt;Embrace reality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all love to fall for lies and distort reality so that it fits our vision of the world. It’s easier for us to live in our echo chamber and believe that we are “killing it” rather than face the harsh reality that we are not as good as we thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether in your professional or personal life, it’s crucial to face the facts, no matter how brutal they are. The earlier you diagnose a potential issue, the faster you can address them and move forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recent economic crash demonstrates how people love to cuddle themselves in an echo chamber and avoid the hard reality that businesses are not viable. It’s common to find people unhappy in their friendship or romantic relationship without realizing they are not in the right place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This principle is reinforced by the “who before the what” principle. When the right people are on your bus, they will help you face some harsh realities. The wrong people will ignore these hard truths and continue business as usual, only to drive the bus in the ravine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;culture-and-discipline-are-essential&quot;&gt;Culture and discipline are essential&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The culture of a company is essential. And it always starts at the top. Employees in a company mimic what their leaders do. When leaders are not embracing a solid culture, employees begin to be all over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Company culture and values will shape who will be on the bus (e.g. who will apply for a job and who gets hired). Today more than ever, some companies put strong culture and values statements, and some employees apply (or not) to a job because of them. Setting up the culture and values of the company is a challenging task, and that is also why some companies are failing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discipline and accountability are also essential and must start from the top. If an executive fails to deliver, they should be held accountable and driven by example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;your-company-is-a-team-not-a-family&quot;&gt;Your company is a team, not a family.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s essential to have the right people on board (see “who before what”) and to be radically honest if one person is not performing as expected for the team. Your team should be the winning one, not the losing one, and for that, you need A-players. And you need A-players at every position on the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have seen companies with more than half of the people not adding real value. When such companies lay off the right people (e.g., non-performing ones), they often operate better because the poor performers no longer drag the high performers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Identifying the right team is &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; hard, either when hiring or firing. But it’s essential to assemble the best team: you cannot win the Superbowl when your players are slow or do not know how to pass the ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;its-all-about-love&quot;&gt;It’s all about love&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I firmly believe that what drives people is love. In the end, love always wins. Love does not mean that everything is all roses. It means caring, supporting, and giving a damn about something or someone. Love for what you are doing and who you are with. And always act for the best interest of the person or business you love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Love does not mean accepting everything. Love can (and should) be tough sometimes. After all, who never had a strong argument with a colleague or partner? It’s normal, and you have this argument because you care and love the topic/person/cause. But in the end, the love and passion you have is a component that makes you discuss opinions, make decisions, and drive to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 28 May 2022 05:13:20 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://julien.gunnm.org/principles/life/company/startup/2022/05/28/principles/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://julien.gunnm.org/principles/life/company/startup/2022/05/28/principles/</guid>
        
        <category>startup</category>
        
        <category>principles</category>
        
        
        <category>principles</category>
        
        <category>life</category>
        
        <category>company</category>
        
        <category>startup</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Follow the process</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Often, I have found that having discipline is what matters the most to reach a goal. Have a process, follow and repeat it every single day.
Most success comes from repeating the same thing every day and doing it, rain or shine. From a personal standpoint, I had only minor victories. However, I reached these personal goals by having a straightforward process and following it every day. I have lost half of my weight (from 300 pounds to 150 pounds) by eating boring meals made of protein-rich food and being active for at least one hour a week for two years. I completed my Ph.D. in 2.5 years because I worked 8 hours every day, including weekends. The ultra-marathons I ran are the results of running at least 70 miles a week for two years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are often tempted to go off-track. Skip a day. Or two. When we give up, we tell ourselves a lie: skipping a day or two will not significantly impact the outcome. In reality, we are not holding ourselves accountable and not respecting the contract we made with ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your process/guidelines can (and will) change over time. The willingness to follow your process should not change. And the dedication to do what you committed to doing should remain the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discipline is not only what will help you progress every single day. It will also guide you when you are lost. If you do not know if what you are doing is worth anything or if you are making the right decisions, all you have to do is to have discipline and follow your process. There is always light at the end of the tunnel.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2022 05:13:20 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://julien.gunnm.org/discipline/culture/process/2022/05/12/follow-the-process/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://julien.gunnm.org/discipline/culture/process/2022/05/12/follow-the-process/</guid>
        
        <category>startup</category>
        
        <category>discipline</category>
        
        
        <category>discipline</category>
        
        <category>culture</category>
        
        <category>process</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>On Culture</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Culture is everything. It makes us feel connected. It gives us a sense of belonging, and a sense of purpose.
Either in society or companies, culture is what bonds a set of people with values they all believe in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a business standpoint, culture is also what can make or break a company.
Which is more important in startups: a startup is a cult, a religion.
A startup needs to have true believers, people who trust a company can make the impossible possible.
And companies with a well-defined and strong culture are the ones that are the most likely to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take Amazon. New hires must read the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aboutamazon.com/about-us/leadership-principles&quot;&gt;leadership principles&lt;/a&gt;,
a set of core values every single employee must follow. All Amazonians operate, breathe and live by these principles.
If you do not embrace them, you will not only have a hard time working there but will ultimately
be let go. There are simple, actionable rules everybody must apply in their daily work.
For example, no slides are presented during meetings: all meetings start with a 1, 3 or 6 pages document that
all employees must read before the meeting. Efficiency at its best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take Coinbase. Two years ago, its CEO made it clear that Coimbase is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.coinbase.com/coinbase-is-a-mission-focused-company-af882df8804&quot;&gt;mission-focused company&lt;/a&gt;
and that activities that do not help or support the company’s mission will not be tolerated. At this time,
this document made waves and a huge backlash ensued. But today, employees know what is the mission
of the company and what is expected from them. And new employees joining Coinbase know exactly
what to expect and what rules will be used to evaluate their performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take Shopify. Less than a year ago, Shopify CEO also made it clear that political discourse is
not welcome within the company. More importantly, he emphasized that the company was not a family
but a team. The team must play at its best and when a player is no longer an A player, they must
be let go. This clearly shows how employees are evaluated and what rules they should follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When culture is not defined or weak (e.g. no reinforcement), others will define
the culture for you. There will be no common understanding of working rules and
chaos will slowly but surely ensue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keeping a strong culture makes sure that everybody (1) knows the rules of the game and (2) will follow these rules,
which is better for the company operators and the employees. For the company operator, it ensures that every single
employee or contractor shares the company vision and is dedicated to making the company successful.
For employees, it ensures that they are not wasting their time working in an environment
they dislike. Some people may not like the culture and ultimately leave, which is
a short-term issue and an opportunity to have new people with a better alignment with the company values.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 30 Apr 2022 05:13:20 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://julien.gunnm.org/startup/culture/2022/04/30/culture/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://julien.gunnm.org/startup/culture/2022/04/30/culture/</guid>
        
        <category>startup</category>
        
        <category>company</category>
        
        <category>culture</category>
        
        
        <category>startup</category>
        
        <category>culture</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>So, you want to start a company?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Many people want to start a company. They have &lt;em&gt;an idea&lt;/em&gt;, believe that making a product is easy and
if you know how to write some lines of code, overnight success is guaranteed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is here to put some reality in perspective. Entrepreneurship is overly romanticized through thousands of articles
detailing the overnight success of a founder, company, or product. But it’s often not what you imagine
and the success is the result of nights of grind, hard work, sweat, and tears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting a company is incredibly hard. The vast majority of companies do not survive. A team works relentlessly
hard on a product for months, only to see no users sign up (other than their family and friends).
It crushes their hope of building something useful when all they need is the mental energy to keep iterating and make a
product that delights users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building the right product is way more complicated than it seems. You may have worked in big companies
that have thousands or millions of users but you have no idea how they started and got the initial users.
Finding the right feature, what &lt;em&gt;users&lt;/em&gt; (and not you) find useful is often counter-intuitive and requires many iterations
and experimentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assembling the right team is critical and is no easy task. You have constrained resources as you cannot offer
the same compensation as other big tech companies. You need to hire &lt;em&gt;“believers”&lt;/em&gt;, people that will understand and follow your vision, no matter how crazy it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marketing and selling a product is a complex task that is totally different from writing lines of code. You need
to understand how to present a product, how to define and refine a sales process to close your first customers.
That is no easy task and you constantly need to learn from others how to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you go and raise money from Venture Capital, you need to talk to investors and articulate your vision to
show the opportunity. At the earliest stage, people will believe and trust you to build the right company
and it’s your responsibility to build trust and show them your progress week after week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, starting a company is &lt;em&gt;fucking&lt;/em&gt; hard. If you are still up for it, know that customers will complain,
your initial product will suck, you will have to fire employees, some people will betray you and investors
will ask when you will be profitable. All of this with a high probability of 0 return whatsoever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do not take me wrong, I have no regret. As somebody that lost half of his weight
within a year (from 300 to 150 pounds) and ran ultra-marathons, I enjoy the pain and
I would not trade places for anything in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2022 05:13:20 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://julien.gunnm.org/startup/saas/2022/03/20/so-you-want-to-start-a-company/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://julien.gunnm.org/startup/saas/2022/03/20/so-you-want-to-start-a-company/</guid>
        
        <category>startup</category>
        
        <category>saas</category>
        
        <category>developer tools</category>
        
        
        <category>startup</category>
        
        <category>saas</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Going on premise early is a bad idea</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;For a long time, I thought going on-premise was the biggest revenue driver for early-stage startups. I had this belief so deep in my brain that I planned to develop an on-premise solution for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.codiga.io&quot;&gt;Codiga&lt;/a&gt;. However, after talking to other founders and advisors, I started to realize this was probably a decision that could sink an early-stage company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that these advices/opinions may not be applicable for all companies or products. The following post explains my reasons, and I am sure it might not apply to many cases. Take this post as a compilation of personal opinions, nothing else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;its-all-about-focus&quot;&gt;It’s all about focus&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building a company (and, to some extent, managing your life) is about resource allocation (how you spend your time, collaborators, and money).
When going on-premise, as the software is no longer deployed in your infrastructure, you need to provide a significant amount of resources to your customers, making sure your solution works seamlessly in their infrastructure. You are not in control of software deployment anymore
and this is your responsibility to make sure your customers are happy. And you will inevitably spend time making sure they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, as you need to sell to big customers and keep the flywheel going, you need to invest in sales:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Develop (and refine) a sales process.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find prospects, schedule demo, follow-up every call, even when customers do not qualify.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Develop marketing to target some specific vital people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your focus shifts from innovation and product-focused company to a sales-focused company. As an early-stage company, your resources are very limited, and investing significant time in sales takes resources away from being innovative. Even if you hire a sales force (which will be limited to one salesperson and one customer manager at this stage), you have to allocate a few engineers to work with them and support the on-premise version of your product. These engineers will not work on innovative features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-finance-does-not-check-out&quot;&gt;The finance does not check out&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine you price your product at $40 per user per seat for your on-premise version. At this price point, to get $500,000 of ARR, it means you need to have more than 1,000 paying users for your on-premise version. With many accounts being around 50 to 100 users, you have roughly 15 accounts to manage and make sure they are happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To manage these 15 accounts, you will need at least one sales representative, two customer managers, and one engineer to debug or troubleshoot issues for your customers. These resources will already cost more than $500,000 per year, which means that even if your on-premise solution yields significant revenue, your business does not make a profit. You not only shifted your focus to sales (see previous point) but you are
also not profitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-future-is-the-public-cloud&quot;&gt;The future is the public cloud&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some customers want to deploy on-premise and will always invoke some reasons for it (the VP of engineering/CEO/CTO invokes security reasons, some engineers claim that they can save large amount of $$$, etc.). The reality is that fewer and fewer companies will stay on-premises. Years ago, the narrative was about security: the public cloud was seen as being insecure/unsafe. Since that time, &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/solutions/case-studies/capital-one-all-in-on-aws/&quot;&gt;Capital One&lt;/a&gt; started to use AWS, new tech companies are starting in the public cloud and existing ones are moving to the public cloud (e.g., Twitter). Even the US government has its public cloud today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trend will continue. Companies noticed the trend and adapted, asking their customers to go to the public cloud. Atlassian is a good example and announces the end of support for the on-premise version of their product. The reality is that on-premise products will become a niche market and more costly to support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The arguments presented above may not apply to all companies and should be taken from a grain of salt.
I believe that early-stage companies should focus on innovation and Product-Market Fit
(e.g., make something users want), not on sales to a specific niche. If your product is &lt;em&gt;that good&lt;/em&gt;, companies
may even have to adapt. 12 years ago, very few companies would have accepted to have all their company conversations
and data stored on machines they do not control and today, the large majority use Google Docs, Office 365
or Slack. These products are so popular that these companies have no choice but to use these products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest issue when developing an on-premise version of a SaaS product at an early stage
is that it forces you to reallocate your resources from developing a great product
to selling and supporting an on-premise version. It will slow you from making a great product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, these arguments may not be correct at later stages when you can afford to
allocate resources to develop a sales and customer support team without impacting innovation.
But at this stage, you may already have enough traction and revenue not even to consider going on-premise.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 Mar 2022 05:13:20 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://julien.gunnm.org/startup/saas/2022/03/12/why-going-on-premise-start-bad-idea/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://julien.gunnm.org/startup/saas/2022/03/12/why-going-on-premise-start-bad-idea/</guid>
        
        <category>startup</category>
        
        <category>saas</category>
        
        <category>developer tools</category>
        
        
        <category>startup</category>
        
        <category>saas</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The founder starter kit</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After a year of founding &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.codiga.io&quot;&gt;Codiga&lt;/a&gt; and running it solo, I now have a pretty good idea about the good tools to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are my guidelines to evaluate the service:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Least friction&lt;/strong&gt;: easy to sign-up and offboard if there is an issue and/or you have better options&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transparency pricing&lt;/strong&gt;: you can see how much you will pay on the website. Starting using the service does not require a call with a sales rep with shady prices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Too many products and services require either (1) a sales call or (2) multiple emails back and forth. Ultimately, if they do not adapt, such services are going to die because:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they cannot scale (manual operations are expensive, which is reflected in the price)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;people do not want interaction ; they want a service that works out of the box&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;before-you-start&quot;&gt;Before you start&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Register your company in Delaware (if you are planning to be backed by venture capital). Online platforms provide services without much pain, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://stripe.com/atlas&quot;&gt;Stripe Atlas&lt;/a&gt;. Being in Delaware is essential if you plan to raise funding.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get a lawyer. There are good firms around for startups such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodwinlaw.com/&quot;&gt;Goodwin&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gunder.com/&quot;&gt;Gunder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get an accountant. A good accountant will take you few thousand dollars a year and ensure everything is on track, reported, and accurate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-services-to-use&quot;&gt;What services to use&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Email&lt;/strong&gt;: GSuite is the industry standard to manage/handle your daily email, calendar, etc. Do not wait to get your google account started. Just pay $12/month.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Security&lt;/strong&gt;: make mandatory that &lt;strong&gt;ALL&lt;/strong&gt; employees/contractors/collaborators to enable 2FA.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Important&lt;/strong&gt;: use Gsuite to sign up for services and use SSO authentication, so that enable/disable accounts is easy.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accounting&lt;/strong&gt;: even if I dislike intuit for their yearly spam notice about taxes, &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickbooks.intuit.com/&quot;&gt;quickbooks&lt;/a&gt; is the standard for bookkeeping.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Slack&lt;/strong&gt;: a must-have for communication today, start paying or switch to Discord. Just set your mind on the right communication channel.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hosting&lt;/strong&gt;: use &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com&quot;&gt;AWS&lt;/a&gt; as they have plenty of discount with many VC. By taking AWS, you are pretty sure you will not pay any cloud expenses until series B. You will likely receive $10,000 to $20,000 credits until you raise series A and an additional $100,000 credits until series B. After that, you should have enough $$$ to cover your cloud bills or find better alternatives. And yes, you might prefer &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;another-cheaper-cloud-provider&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; but (1) they are not as reliable as AWS and (2) they do not offer the same discounts or services.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design&lt;/strong&gt;: sign up for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.figma.com/&quot;&gt;Figma&lt;/a&gt; for your whole team. Just the best design tool I have seen for design. Signing up for any Adobe product pulls you back in the 90s.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Captable management&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://carta.com/&quot;&gt;Carta&lt;/a&gt; is the industry’s gold standard, but (1) they are costly early-stage, and (2) their customer service is terrible. I recommend &lt;a href=&quot;https://cakeequity.com/us&quot;&gt;Cake&lt;/a&gt;, which costs me about $800 a year (vs. $5000 for Carta).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source code management&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; is now the industry standard for source code management and all your employees are familiar with it. A good alternative is GitLab. Avoid Bitbucket because their user interface/user experience is terrible, the support for CI/CD tool is limited and the number of integrations is also very limited.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monitoring&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.datadoghq.com/&quot;&gt;Datadog&lt;/a&gt; is just the best monitoring tool on the market. Easy to configure and use, you get your monitoring stack up and running in less than one hour.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SOC-2 certification&lt;/strong&gt; with &lt;a href=&quot;https://secureframe.com/&quot;&gt;Secureframe&lt;/a&gt;: if you have a SaaS business and needs SOC-2 compliance, Secureframe facilitates all the certification/audit process. SOC-2 used to be a $70,000 to $80,000 line item ; companies like &lt;a href=&quot;https://secureframe.com/&quot;&gt;Secureframe&lt;/a&gt; automate a lot of the process and make it available between $10,000 to $20,000.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 27 Feb 2022 05:13:20 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://julien.gunnm.org/startup/founder/toolbox/2022/02/27/the-founder-starter-kit/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://julien.gunnm.org/startup/founder/toolbox/2022/02/27/the-founder-starter-kit/</guid>
        
        <category>startup</category>
        
        
        <category>startup</category>
        
        <category>founder</category>
        
        <category>toolbox</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>One year as a startup founder</title>
        <description>&lt;div style=&quot;position:relative;padding-bottom:56.25%;height:0;overflow:hidden;&quot;&gt; &lt;iframe style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;left:0px;top:0px;overflow:hidden&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; type=&quot;text/html&quot; src=&quot;https://www.dailymotion.com/embed/video/xtftd?autoplay=1&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been a year since I left Twitter to start my own company. Within a year, I have been
through the startup rollercoaster: joining an accelerator, discussing with corporate
development about aquisition offers, and of course, fundraising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During Techstars, a repeated startup founder/CEO told me this truth:
&lt;em&gt;“A startup CEO has three jobs: explain the vision, hire and fire, don’t run out of money”&lt;/em&gt;.
One year after, I firmly believe this is true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on this year, there are a few takeaways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;think-first-principles&quot;&gt;Think first principles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When starting a company and going through an accelerator, you get exposed to hundreds
of opinions from the accelerator itself, other founders, employees, advisors, mentors, and investors. It’s your responsibility to evaluate them and make sound decisions for your business.
It’s easy to get lost in the myriad of opinions others have about your company and product, especially
so early.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to walk through this jungle of advice, weed 90+% and keep the best. To do that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First_principle&quot;&gt;first principles&lt;/a&gt; and come back to your core ideas.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Base your strategy on metrics and not what some random person told you to do.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take decisions that follow the culture you want to instill in your company.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I just explained seems essential, and still, I see many founders getting distracted
and lost by bad advice. One book that helps think with first principles
is &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/3KAsiig&quot;&gt;Principles&lt;/a&gt; from Ray Dahlio. I read this book in 2021, and it helped me get back on track when lost under hundreds of opinions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;no-hire-is-better-than-a-bad-hire&quot;&gt;No hire is better than a bad hire&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hiring is hard. This is one of the most challenging problems in the startup world,
especially at the very early stages. One bad hire can ruin your culture, team, and runway.
One good hire can work hard and do their best to deliver a delightful product your customers will love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to have the conviction that the people you hire are among the best
to work on the problem you are solving. If you do not have this conviction, you waste your time and money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When choosing an employee or co-founder, you need to admire this person for what they
can deliver in their domain. Like a relationship, you do not need to agree on
everything, but you need to (1) admire and recognize them as an expert in their domain and in the value they deliver and
(2) ensure that they fit with the company culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the french saying goes: &lt;em&gt;“Mieux vaut être seul que mal accompagné”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dont-get-distracted-and-learn-to-say-no&quot;&gt;Don’t get distracted and learn to say no&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t get distracted. You often get distracted by an opinion from an investor,
a specific ask from one company, or just by the flow of meetings people want to have with you.
It’s a trap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an idea comes, evaluate the value it can bring to your business. It’s easy to go down a rabbit hole to implement a new feature, product, or hire a specific person. But if this proposition does not bring value to your business: say no and move on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Football players do not get distracted on the field. Be the same: you are here for the home run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;focus-on-pmf-build-something-people-love&quot;&gt;Focus on PMF, build something people love&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One main takeaway from Techstars has been focusing on Product-Market Fit (PMF).
Put it in simple terms; it just means people want what you are building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make a product people love, delight customers with valuable, carefully crafted features.
Your primary focus at the seed stage must be to get to PMF. If you get to PMF, sales will (normally) follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some companies do not have PMF. Some raise giant financing rounds without having PMF.
All of this is great, but one day, the reality of the market comes back,
and the company has a hard time closing any sale. To avoid that trap, don’t get distracted
and focus on PMF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some books that help me navigate this first year as a founder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/3KAsiig&quot;&gt;Principles by Ray Dhalio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/40Grq0V&quot;&gt;Never split the difference - Chris Voss&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/3mc9RqM&quot;&gt;High Output Management&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jan 2022 05:13:20 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://julien.gunnm.org/startup/founder/codiga/techstars/2022/01/16/one-year-as-a-founder/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://julien.gunnm.org/startup/founder/codiga/techstars/2022/01/16/one-year-as-a-founder/</guid>
        
        <category>startup</category>
        
        <category>founder</category>
        
        <category>techstars</category>
        
        
        <category>startup</category>
        
        <category>founder</category>
        
        <category>codiga</category>
        
        <category>techstars</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Reality Distortion</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In personal or professional relations, I realized that failure comes from the distortion of reality. You and 1+ other person(s) do not have the same vision of reality. Our vision of reality is biased, and we want to see the truth and facts better than they look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your company fails because your vision of the market did not match the reality, or/and your product sucks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your customer did not sign the contract; you thought they liked your product way more than you think&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your friend did not contact you because you are way less attractive or interesting than you think and they don’t have time for you&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your partner wants to separate despite you thinking your relation was significant.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The list could go on and on. The fact is that you and 1+ person(s) do not share the same reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all have biases and mental shortcuts that let us live in a distorted reality.
The longer we live in this false reality, the more challenging and expensive it costs to escape it.
Over the last years, it has hit me hard in friendship, relationships, or business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the solution here? While I do not have the perfect plan, there are some solutions I use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Match &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; reality with &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; metrics&lt;/strong&gt;: measure what you think is happening in the world and compare it to your vision and opinions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;External monitoring&lt;/strong&gt;: have a friend or partner give &lt;em&gt;honest&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;non-biased&lt;/em&gt; feedback. And listen to them. The hardest part is getting somebody open and not afraid to tell you how wrong you can be. Cherish such relationships.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Periodically evaluate yourself&lt;/strong&gt;: regularly question your view of reality and how distorted it can be.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While sometimes you can be wrong, the world can also adopt your vision of reality. It happened in the past (after all, we are switching to electric cars, France dropped the Minitel for Internet), but it’s infrequent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always remember that we are all humans. When facing how wrong you are, be honest with yourself: face the reality you did not see, realize your mistake and blame no one but yourself. Cut your losses and move on. It is not about how hard wrong you were but how quickly you realize it and move forward.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 05 Dec 2021 05:13:20 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://julien.gunnm.org/reality/distortion/essay/2021/12/05/reality-distortion/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://julien.gunnm.org/reality/distortion/essay/2021/12/05/reality-distortion/</guid>
        
        <category>reality</category>
        
        <category>distortion</category>
        
        
        <category>reality</category>
        
        <category>distortion</category>
        
        <category>essay</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why Code Inspector?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: this post is part of a series about the foundations for Code Inspector, you
can find the previous article &lt;a href=&quot;/software engineering/essay/humans/human behavior/2020/12/26/the-machine-is-better-than-you/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the last post in the series about Code Inspector. The &lt;a href=&quot;/software engineering/essay/humans/human behavior/2020/12/17/we-are-all-stupid/&quot;&gt;first post&lt;/a&gt;
focused on why humans are fallible by design and sub-optimal at executing
small and repetitive tasks. The &lt;a href=&quot;/software engineering/essay/humans/human behavior/2020/12/26/the-machine-is-better-than-you/&quot;&gt;second post&lt;/a&gt; focused on the
exponential progress of automation: tasks performed by machines
are getting more complex every day and soon, most of our jobs are
going to be automated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next paragraphs, I explain the main drivers for starting Code Inspector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-software-maintenance-problem&quot;&gt;The software maintenance problem&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a real struggle to develop software, especially because it is really
hard to find and understand the design and implementation choices made by the initial
authors. Software is often poorly documented, which makes it very complicated
to troubleshoot an issue or maintain an old codebase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The average tenure for software developers is between 2 to 3 years. But
the software is operated and maintained for decades. As developers leave a
company their knowledge of a project leaves the company. &lt;strong&gt;In some industries,
the developers that maintain software were not even born when the initial
system was designed.&lt;/strong&gt;. (Think twice about this!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some developers have no idea how the system they operate actually works.
It can take days or weeks to troubleshoot an issue because the system is way
too complex and the documentation, non-existent. And it is not common that issues
go unnoticed for months because developers do not understand the impact
of their scope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an obvious need for a product that helps developers understand
a code base and establish a plan to improve it. This product needs to be
user-friendly, non-intimidating and to give clear actionable paths to improve
their codebase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-software-modernization-problem&quot;&gt;The software modernization problem&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Software is like our physical infrastructure: it’s aging and
improving legacy software is a major undertaking. Reports estimates
that bad code and technical debt takes up to 30% of developer time
(see &lt;a href=&quot;https://stripe.com/files/reports/the-developer-coefficient.pdf&quot;&gt;Stripe study&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://redfin.engineering/pay-down-your-technical-debt-faster-by-limiting-your-payments-84fdca5e4ea3&quot;&gt;other sources&lt;/a&gt; estimate it’s more like 20%).
The same &lt;a href=&quot;https://stripe.com/files/reports/the-developer-coefficient.pdf&quot;&gt;study from Stripe&lt;/a&gt;
reports that bad code costs companies $85B annually. Even if you cut the estimate
in half, it’s still a number that makes you wonder if we should continue to write
code as we do today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two solutions to address the modernization problem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hire more engineers, which increases costs exponentially and increases productivity linearly (at best).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Automate software development.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until very recently, only the first solution was possible. The recent
progress on software analysis and machine learning allows to automate
software development. This is a natural evolution: after all, today, Google translate
writes better English than I do and a Tesla drives better than I do
(on a highway for now). Why couldn’t a computer program better than I do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first, only a few aspects will be automated. As the technology
develops, the scope of automation will grow and the human factor
in software development will shrink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-training-problem&quot;&gt;The training problem&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The change from manual to automated software development is not going to happen
overnight. Demand for software engineers will still be strong for the next ten
to twenty years and the two problems mentioned before (maintenance + modernization)
will require more engineers over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department of labor &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bls.gov/ooh/computer-and-information-technology/software-developers.htm&quot;&gt;already predicts&lt;/a&gt;
that demand for software engineers will grow by 20% in the next ten years.
The traditional education system cannot absorb this increase. The job
market for software engineers will be heavy on the demand (a lot of job
openings) and limited on the offer (not enough engineers).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that many engineers will be under-trained and there will
be a need for additional training. A code automation platform
can help engineers to become better by providing guidance.
Such a platform will not only guide them in their work but also help them become
better software engineers by explaining why some modifications are recommended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-mission&quot;&gt;The mission&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mission of Code Inspector is clear: &lt;strong&gt;help developers produce better software&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three main aspects to achieve this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identification&lt;/strong&gt;: detect issues in a codebase, surface
them in a user-friendly interface and help developers prioritize software maintenance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automation&lt;/strong&gt;: automate resolution of bugs and
maintenance issues. Let the machine fix issues for you: it will do it better than
the majority of humans.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Training&lt;/strong&gt;: incentivize developers to maintain a codebase, fix issues
and guide them through code changes (e.g. explain why they are done).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The financial impact is clear as well: with an average salary of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bls.gov/ooh/computer-and-information-technology/software-developers.htm&quot;&gt;$108,000 per year&lt;/a&gt;,
a product that makes engineers 1% more productive would already unlock a value
of $1,000 per engineer per year. And if such a product could even cut the time spent
in technical debt by 50%, it will then save $10,000 per developer per year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a huge, underestimated problem and this
is why I left everything to focus on this project. The coming year is going
to be very exciting and I can’t wait for it to start.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 26 Dec 2020 05:13:20 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://julien.gunnm.org/software%20engineering/essay/humans/human%20behavior/2020/12/26/why-code-inspector/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://julien.gunnm.org/software%20engineering/essay/humans/human%20behavior/2020/12/26/why-code-inspector/</guid>
        
        <category>software engineering</category>
        
        <category>essay</category>
        
        <category>code inspector</category>
        
        
        <category>software engineering</category>
        
        <category>essay</category>
        
        <category>humans</category>
        
        <category>human behavior</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
